<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/articles</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/articles"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2019-05-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>The challenge: apply to trade on your own market</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/articles/the-challenge-apply-to-trade-on-your-own-market/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/articles/the-challenge-apply-to-trade-on-your-own-market/</id>
    <published>2019-05-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-15T06:35:51+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;object type="image/png" data="apply-key.png"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a title="Apply Key" href="https://flickr.com/photos/157270154@N05/26706270559"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Apply Key&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://flickr.com/people/157270154@N05"&gt;Mike Lawrence&lt;/a&gt; shared under a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/"&gt;Creative Commons (BY-SA) licence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you currently run a market, try applying to trade on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How easy was it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did you have to collect an application form?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was all the information you provided relevant?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did all the questions make sense?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where you asked to provide documents with no clue as to how to get them (insurance, food registration &amp;amp;c.)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you tell traders up front what you are, &lt;em&gt;and aren’t&lt;/em&gt;, looking for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you encourage people to be street traders and provide them with information about start-up loans and mentoring?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have an information stall on your market? If you’re a local authority market you could offer an information stall as a free charity collection pitch for rotating charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you only offer paper applications and have no internal team to develop a digital one for your website, take a look at online form providers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://jotform.com"&gt;JotForm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.typeform.com"&gt;Typeform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are already using online forms, are you using branching logic to ask the minimum questions such as only asking good traders about registration as a food business? Are you telling applicants all the information that they need to have ready before starting to complete the form?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you making it too hard to ask for a stall and and what could you do to make it easier to apply and to make applications easier to process?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building versus hosting a market</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/articles/building-versus-hosting-a-market/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/articles/building-versus-hosting-a-market/</id>
    <published>2019-05-08T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-08T07:41:52+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="hiller-bros.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Hiller Bros former yard at 64 Squirries Street, London circa 1900. © Tower Hamlets Local History Library.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the strongest sources of sustenance to a thriving market is how easy it is for new traders to rock up and start trading. However, if you don’t provide stall equipment and storage space your market can only host established traders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-change"&gt;The change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the nineties, London Councils have steadily removed the traditional barrows from street markets. This has led to a dramatic decline in the number of barrow manufacturers and suppliers with—as far as a I know—only Bakers off of Roman Road still trading. Previously most markets had yards where barrows could be stored and barrows remain cheap to rent (under ten pounds a week) with repairs carried out for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-response"&gt;The response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href="https://broadwaymarket.co.uk"&gt;Broadway Market&lt;/a&gt; we sourced market stalls and paid a crew to put them up, complete with tarpaulin and lights. We allocated the assembled stalls to traders. On &lt;a href="http://exmouth.london"&gt;Exmouth Market&lt;/a&gt; you were allocated a pitch and brought your own stall equipment with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-result"&gt; The result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Broadway Market the majority of the traders were new to market trading, on Exmouth Market every trader was already established elsewhere. Broadway was mainly incubating new traders and Exmouth was providing existing traders with an opportunity to expand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not going to provide the equipment and somewhere to store it, you are going to be relying on other markets to nurture traders for you and your market might create jobs but is unlikely to create businesses. Your lock-up or yard might be the sexiest part of your market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="baker-and-sons.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Better living through street food</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/articles/better-living-through-street-food/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/articles/better-living-through-street-food/</id>
    <published>2019-04-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-04-29T07:29:14+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="vegan-salad.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Photograph credit: &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://flickr.com/photos/160866001@N07/32734311987"&gt;Vegan Salad&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by &lt;a href="https://flickr.com/people/160866001@N07"&gt;Marco Verch&lt;/a&gt; shared under a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"&gt;Creative Commons (BY) licence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-pitch"&gt;The pitch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the likes of black pudding &amp;amp; duck ‘scotch’ eggs and halloumi fries have their place as indulgent treats, many street food markets are now offering little in the way of healthier alternatives to these deep-fired delights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most markets are oversubscribed with applications from potential food traders so you can afford to be a little picky when it comes to takeaway food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="determine-what-counts-as-healthy-catering"&gt;Determine what counts as healthy catering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://healthiercateringcommitment.co.uk"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Healthy Catering Commitment&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a formalized set of criteria which takes food fads and personal preference out of the equation. The Commitment is a scheme run by the London Boroughs with support from the Mayor of London that recognises businesses that demonstrate a commitment to reducing the level of saturated fat and salt in their food, to offer some healthier options like lower sugar drinks and snacks, and to make smaller portions available on request. There is some useful &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/healthier-and-more-sustainable-catering-a-toolkit-for-serving-food-to-adults"&gt;information regarding sustainability and nutrition on gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="food-hygiene"&gt;Food hygiene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of healthy catering is that the food is safe to eat, regardless of its nutritional impact. Consider requiring traders to meet a minimum score on their &lt;a href="https://www.food.gov.uk/safety-hygiene/food-hygiene-rating-scheme"&gt;food hygiene rating&lt;/a&gt; such as four which equates to good. I’m a strong proponent in requiring traders to display their score on their stalls. I think it’s good practice for market management and for traders themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="applications"&gt;Applications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve yet to see a Healthy Catering application form that was anything other than challenging to fill in or to assess. For example, the model form on the Healthier Catering Commitment website has the acceptable answers for “Tel” and “E-mail” as “Yes”, “No”, or “N/A”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make life a little easier, I have cobbled together a &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/"&gt;Google Form&lt;/a&gt; that automagically scores each applicant and then adds the answers to a spreadsheet feel free to copy and adapt it: &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1gMYnLVWZlejZOlzU0nii6mfI9JPuSXc2-A906S3b7OA/copy"&gt;Healthier Catering Commitment application form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;object type="image/png" data="form.png"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a customer facing environment you would want to avoid Google Forms as Google are struggling with data protection compliance. For file uploads the people filling in the form have to have a Google account which is an unnecessary hurdle for applicants. There are plenty of alternatives such as &lt;a href="https://www.jotform.com/"&gt;JotForm&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.typeform.com/"&gt;Typeform&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am planning to write-up guidance and encouragement to make sure that all application forms and information about trading is presented in an accessible (legally and linguistically) manner but for the sake of simplicity the above forms just tackles the Commitment to Healthier Catering. However, I think there is no harm in requiring all takeaway food applications to meet the minimum criteria and integrating it into your standard applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="regulating-food-vendors-near-schools"&gt;Regulating food vendors near schools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="burts-burgers.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Photograph credit: &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://flickr.com/photos/elsie/8603505961"&gt;Burts burgers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/people/elsie"&gt;Les Chatfield&lt;/a&gt; shared under a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"&gt;Creative Commons (BY) licence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mayor of &lt;a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/what-we-do/business-and-economy/food/support-and-resources/takeaways-toolkit"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;London’s Takeaways Toolkit (2012)&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt; recommends using street trading legislation (if your local authority has adopted it) to restrict mobile fast food vans, particularly around schools:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite="https://www.london.gov.uk/what-we-do/business-and-economy/food/support-and-resources/takeaways-toolkit"&gt;Mobile fast food units are not governed by planning policy, but can be controlled by the granting of street trading licences by local authorities and regulated by environmental health and trading standards officers. Local authorities have the power to restrict the areas where mobile vans trade by designating streets as ‘prohibited’, ‘consent’ or ‘licensed’ with respect to street trading. If a local authority passes a resolution to make some streets prohibited, then no street trading can take place in those areas. This can be a means of regulating fast food vans around the school fringe. When a local authority designates streets as licensed or consent streets, they can regulate the number of street traders in that area. In doing so, a local authority can restrict fast food vans and give preference to those offering healthier options.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="restriction-of-competition-considerations"&gt;Restriction of competition considerations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;European competition law can make some local authorities timid about placing restrictions on the kinds of applications they will block and the regulations they will apply to restrict businesses. The important things is know that you have a legitimate interest in promoting healthy eat and healthy living in general and that the above suggestions are reasonable attempts to fulfil a market regulators responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re curating a market, not every takeaway food stall has to be something fried, in a bun, with chips. You can and should do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of small things you can do to promote health through a market such as providing bicycle racks, promoting &lt;a href="https://www.healthystart.nhs.uk/"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Healthy Start&lt;/cite&gt; vouchers&lt;/a&gt;, and holding cooking classes. &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:6516976502582583296/"&gt;Esther Morrison&lt;/a&gt; makes a good point about the importance of cooking and education: “A general market thrives on food—not just artisan &amp;amp; street food, but the footfall from the daily purchasing of ingredients to cook. This ‘buy less, more often’ reduces food waste and costs, but without the confidence to cook, the temptation is to think ‘I’m not worth the effort’ and to walk on past, to the supermarket ready meals.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is one &lt;em&gt;big thing&lt;/em&gt; that you can do improve the health of visitors to your market, improve the nutritional value of the food that they munch on as they walk around the stalls.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Designing a street market</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/articles/designing-a-street-market/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/articles/designing-a-street-market/</id>
    <published>2019-04-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-04-26T13:08:22+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="broadway-market-north.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Photograph credit: &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.janeillustration.co.uk/blog/dalston-drawings-3/broadway-north-1024x726/"&gt;Broadway Market North&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by &lt;a href="http://www.janeillustration.co.uk/"&gt;Jane Smith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article describes an example layout for a small food and craft market of 78 stalls with 36 earmarked for food and 42 for non-food. The layout is, loosely, based upon one experimented with on Broadway Market in East London. The example plan I have included is for Lower Marsh near Waterloo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as the sample layout, there are some pointers for best curatorial practice/trader mix to create a lively market that gives traders optimal opportunities to sell their goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="trader-mix"&gt;Trader mix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The market is composed of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;twelve takeaway food stalls,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;three fruit &amp;amp; veg traders,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;three butchers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;three bread stalls,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fifteen other food produce stalls such as cheesemongers and cakes, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;42 non-food stalls.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a market, stalls should compliment both the shops and each other. Try not to duplicate stalls. You can differentiate between similar traders like cheesemongers using provenance or price. A market should serve its community and most communities around markets are diverse in terms of income as well as in terms of backgrounds and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="layout"&gt;Layout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where access for fire engines allows, stalls should be back-to-back in the middle of the road rather than facing each other backing onto the kerb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the stalls are facing each other it can be more photogenic but it splits foot traffic three ways and smothers trade for the shops behind the stalls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="columbia-road.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Photograph credit: &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/visualpunch/5628934853/"&gt;Columbia Road flower market&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/visualpunch/"&gt;visualpun.ch&lt;/a&gt; shared under a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/"&gt;Creative Commons (BY-SA) licence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Columbia Road is a fantastic market but almost impassable when busy and few would argue that the shops behind the stalls get a fair slice of the action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stalls back-to-back create an easier customer journey (you can walk around the whole market in one trip without doubling-back. This layout also provides added security for the traders as the back of their stall backs onto another stall and is less accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="broadway-market.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Photograph credit: &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/feesta/3446596993/"&gt;Saturday is the market day&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/feesta/"&gt;Jeff Easter&lt;/a&gt; shared under a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/"&gt;Creative Commons (BY-SA) licence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The layout at the North end of Broadway Market maximizes the footway available to visitors and leaves enough room for the shops that some of them have seating outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example market is in three blocks. At the centre of each block there are four takeaway food traders, these are then flanked by produce traders with non-food traders on the outside. A couple of double stalls are added to each block to reflect that these are often required for bakers, butchers, and grocers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;object type="image/png" data="layout.png"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where possible, you shouldn’t put cooking next to non-food stalls. The cooking smells will distract their customers and can cause their stock, especially clothing, to smell. Successful takeaway stalls can also generate queues and these need to be managed to prevent them blocking the frontages of other stalls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-food traders often struggle on a mixed market so you should reserve the corner and end pitches for high-quality non-food stalls which are selling mid to high price items. They generally take far less money than food stalls so it is reasonable to give them prominent locations. You could also use these stalls for charity and informational purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where other roads lead onto the market and form junctions, set stalls across the junctions. You are trying to create a journey around the market rather than encourage people to pass quickly through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;object type="image/png" data="junction.png"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="seating"&gt;Seating&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each block is separated from the others by seating. Whenever you have space or fewer than usual stalls, make up the difference with seating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;object type="image/png" data="seating.png"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seating may not generate stall income, but it increases the time that people stay on the market and leads to greater sales. You should always consider sacrificing some stall space to seating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seating should always be within the market rather than near an exit. You want people to move past stalls to access the seating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="equipment"&gt;Equipment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="cooking-and-refrigeration"&gt;Cooking and refrigeration&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where possible provide electricity for tills, weighing scales, and lights only. Cooking should be done using gas appliances and food stored in cooler boxes or with ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fridges and freezers used by street traders tend to be domestic equipment not designed to have their doors open and closed so much—commercial equipment features more powerful compressors that have the ability to maintain a consistent temperature even when opened on frequent intervals—so their use is probably providing a false sense of comfort anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electric cooking equipment doesn’t hold up to being transported and treated roughly, it tends to lead to power surges and tripped fuses. If you are going to have a number of stalls cooking with electric you will need to monitor usage carefully and have an electrician available to deal with any issues that arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="lighting"&gt;Lighting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is generally better to provide lighting rather than leave traders to their own devices. By stringing together festoon lights, each block of stalls can be lit using just one plug. Providing lighting also means that the stalls stay lit till the market closes rather than have individual stalls going dark as they close. Lots of sales can be lost when a few traders pack-up early and markets look like they&amp;#39;ve already closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="raekoja-plats.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Photograph credit: &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/guillaumespeurt/32252118841/"&gt;Christmas market on raekoja plats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/guillaumespeurt/"&gt;Guillaume Speurt&lt;/a&gt; shared under a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/"&gt;Creative Commons (BY-SA) licence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id="setup-and-breakdown"&gt;Setup and breakdown&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The layout that I have indicated should take a stall crew of four two hours to erect and to dismantle. This depends on the exact equipment used and how much additional work is required such as lighting and tarpaulins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;object type="image/png" data="market-layout.png"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Market design is craft rather than science and in many cases the current layout has arisen by accident and tradition. Above are some general observations based on experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The geography of a particular street will place limitations on your layout as well as creating opportunities. For example, outside a busy pub you would want to avoid placing craft or produce stalls due to the disruption and possible rowdy behaviour. However, hot food stalls would probably flourish in the same location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some traders can be very resistant to change due to a long experience of it being usually negative. However, supermarkets regularly change their layouts for a reason. Frequent visitors to the market can start to travel around it like automatons. Change encourages people to take new journeys and visit new stalls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have anything to add please message me or comment and I will update the article if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The trust issue</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/articles/the-trust-issue/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/articles/the-trust-issue/</id>
    <published>2019-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-04-26T10:52:44+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="the-trust-issue.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people who are not used to shopping on a local market, the retail environment presented by stalls can be disconcerting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With many stalls, it can be difficult to identify the trader—especially if they are a lurker and not in the habit of being in, or next to, their stall. It can also be difficult to find contact details without directly asking the trader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst the right to return goods is the same for a stall as it is for a shop; uncertainty over this is a reason that customers are often cautious about making purchases, especially those that are expensive or likely to require after-sales care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="how-managers-can-help"&gt;How managers can help&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Display clear contact information for the market management team so that visitors to the market know that the market is regulated and who they can turn to for information or help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="all-stalls"&gt;All stalls&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing policies where stalls have clear name plates, with contact details to identify them,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identifying name tags or branded aprons for the owners of stalls,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a requirement to display clear prices for products,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;helping traders to understand how card payments can boost sales and how simple using card payment systems can be, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;requiring any provenance or health claims to be evidenced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="non-food-stalls"&gt;Non-food stalls&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="africa-at-spitalfields.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Photograph credit: &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/spitalfields-e1/9624589344/"&gt;Africa at Spitalfields&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/spitalfields-e1/"&gt;Spitalfields_E1&lt;/a&gt; shared under a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/"&gt;Creative Commons (BY-SA) licence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A template returns policy provided to traders as well as promise of continued record, in case of future dispute; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing those selling precious metals with hallmark explanation cards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="food-stalls"&gt;Food stalls&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="borough-market.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Photograph credit: &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mastermaq/3600010535/"&gt;Borough Market&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mastermaq/"&gt;Mack Male&lt;/a&gt; shared under a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/"&gt;Creative Commons (BY-SA) licence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Northern Ireland and Wales it is compulsory for food business to display their, most recent, &lt;a href="https://www.food.gov.uk/safety-hygiene/food-hygiene-rating-scheme"&gt;food hygiene rating&lt;/a&gt;. In England it is voluntary and, at least half of businesses do not. Create a requirement that your market’s food stalls must display their score. It legitimizes the stall as a real regulated food business and encourages confidence in customers. If the score is painfully low, they probably shouldn’t be trading anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the &lt;a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:32011R1169&amp;amp;amp;from=en"&gt;&lt;abbr title="European Union"&gt;E.U.&lt;/abbr&gt;, rashly, allowed member states to draft their own rules for the labelling of potentially fatal allergens in non-prepackaged food&lt;/a&gt;. The U.K. opted to introduce, and not enforce, very weak guidance. Require traders to list those allergens alongside each menu item where they are an ingredient. That would allow visitors who suffer from food allergies to shop with greater confidence on your market than they can on the high street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a few small changes, I believe markets can build an environment where shoppers feel more confident in parting with their money and traders are maximizing their opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Curatorial control-freakery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/articles/curatorial-control-freakery/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/articles/curatorial-control-freakery/</id>
    <published>2019-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-04-26T10:50:29+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="camden-market-west-yard.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe we should let go to let market’s thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;London’s Public street markets are mostly regulated under the &lt;a href="https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukla/2007/2/contents/enacted"&gt;London Local Authorities Act&lt;/a&gt;. Many industry leaders chaff under its restrictions and hanker for greater control over product such as that manifested at the private markets like &lt;a href="https://www.camdenmarket.com"&gt;Camden Lock &amp;amp; Stables&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://oldspitalfieldsmarket.com"&gt;Old Spitalfields Market&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="old-spitalfields-market.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Photograph credit: &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/londonmatt/40472892230/"&gt;Spitalfields Market&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/londonmatt/"&gt;Matt Brown&lt;/a&gt; shared under a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/"&gt;Creative Commons (BY-SA) licence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reports on the state of London markets often call for reform of the Act to allow local councils the same curatorial power. It was a recommendation of the &lt;a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/sites/default/files/20171219_gla_markets_report_web.pdf"&gt;Greater London Authority &lt;cite&gt;Understanding London’s Markets&lt;/cite&gt; (2017)&lt;/a&gt; as well as the &lt;a href="http://www.crossriverpartnership.org/media/2014/12/Sustainable-Urban-Markets-An-Action-Plan-for-London3.pdf"&gt;Cross River Partnership’s &lt;cite&gt;Sustainable Urban Markets: an Action plan for London&lt;/cite&gt; (2014)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I look at the thriving and relevant markets at Bethnal Green and Whitechapel, I’m not so sure. I could also point to the organically grown lunch markets like Leather Lane, Exmouth Market, and Whitecross Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;object type="image/jpeg" data="whitechapel-road-stalls.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Photograph credit: &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/alanstanton/1309051422/"&gt;Whitechapel Road Stalls&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; by &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/alanstanton/"&gt;Alan Stanton&lt;/a&gt; shared under a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/"&gt;Creative Commons (BY-SA) licence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that local authorities should embrace their limited opportunity to curate. The hours that a market operates, the services provided (electricity, parking, storage, stall equipment), and facilities for visitors (seating, toilets, busking—parking again) all provide powerful—indirect—ways to sculpt a market without micromanaging each application to trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets came into being, and flourished, in environments where they were regulated but not curated. The idea of hand-picking each trader is a very new one that favours established traders operating across several markets and limits opportunities for start-ups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traders working for themselves, or stall assistants on commission, generally work harder and engage with customers more than staff who are hovering on the cusp of minimum wage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The job of a market manager is to remove friction between a sales person with a good idea and them being able to trade:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if they don’t understand the steps that they need to take to setup their business, create a guide;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can’t fill in the form, fix it; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can’t read or write? Fill in the forms for them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get better returns working on presentation with a good salesperson that has a solid product rather than starting by choosing an applicant who has great presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the general vanity of the age, I don’t think that my æsthetic choices should determine whether a business is given a chance or not. The London Local Authorities Act gives traders standing and makes them partners, there is nothing wrong with that.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
